Guide to the Atwood Collins United Nations collection ARCH007
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Atwood Collins United Nations collection
1942-1953, undated
bulk 1945 May - Jun
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Collins, Atwood, II, 1917-2004
ARCH007
3.46 Linear Feet (10 containers)
The collection consists of the papers from Atwood Collins work pertaining to the United Nations Conference on International Organization held in San Francisco, CA in 1945.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical Note
Atwood Collins II, long-time regent of the University of Hartford, was a respected Hartford attorney for many years. In addition to locating the property on which the University of Hartford was built, he crafted many of the legal documents which created the University.
Collins was born in Hartford and earned his BA and law degrees at Yale University. After service in the US Army during World War II, he assisted Army Intelligence in Germany interrogating high-ranking Nazi officials for the Nuremberg War Crimes Trials.
Collins was a member of the US delegation to the 1945 Conference on International Organization in San Francisco, CA, where the charter for the United Nations was signed. He also served as a member of the committee that formed the International Court of Justice.
Historical Note
The United Nations Conference on International Organization was held in San Francisco in 1945, with the purpose of creating a charter for the United Nations (U.N.).
In order to complete the creation of a U.N. charter in just two months the process was split into parts. The Steering Committee consisted of the heads of all of the delegations. The Executive Committee, comprised of just 14 of the head delegates, prepared recommendations for the Steering Committee. The Coordination Committee was responsible for drafting and revisions of documents. The charter was split into four commissions (each with their own additional committees and sub-committees) each covering a different section of the charter: I) General Provisions, II) General Assembly, III) Security Council, IV) Judicial Organization. The original draft of the Statute of the International Court of Justice presented to Commission IV was completed by the U.N Committee of Jurists in Washington, D.C. in April 1945.
The charter was signed at the San Francisco Conference on June 25 1945. However, the U.N. did not come into existence until enough members had ratified it on October 24, 1945.
Additional information on the history of the San Francisco Conference may be found here: http://www.un.org/en/aboutun/history/sanfrancisco_conference.shtml
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of documents pertaining to the United Nations Conference on International Organization held in San Francisco, CA in 1945. The materials are primarily in English, but there are copies of documents that are in French. Most of the documents are from the conference, but there are also notes taken by Atwood Collins, as well as memorandums to/from Atwood Collins during the two-month conference.
The collection also consists of documents and publications from before and after the San Fransisco conference pertaining to the United Nations.
Arrangement
Arranged in 9 series: I. Committees; II. Secretariat & Delegations; III. Commissions; IV. General U.N. Documents; V. Plenary Sessions; VI. Conference News and Notifications; VII. Ephemera; VIII. Publications; IX. Post-Conference U.N.
International relations; United Nations Conference on International Organization -- (1945: -- San Francisco, Calif.); International organization; United Nations
- Committees, 1945 April 4 - Jun 22, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-12)
  - U.N. Committee of Jurists, 1945 Apr 4 - May 4, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Steering Committee, 1945 May 1 - Jun 23 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Executive Committee, 1945 Apr 30 - May 19 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Coordination Committee, 1945 May 10 - Jun 22, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
- Secretariat and Delegations, 1945 Apr 23 - Jun 22 (Box 1, Folder 13-18)
  - Secretariat and Heads of Delegations, 1945 Apr 23 - Jun 19, undated (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
  - U.S. Delegation, 1945 May 5 - Jun 22, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Commissions, 1945 May 4 - Jun 25, undated (Box 1, Folder 19-26, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Folder 1-19)
  Scope and Content
  This series contains the U.N. Conference documents pertaining to the four commissions: 1) Commission I - General Provisions, 2) Commission II - General Assembly, 3) Commission III - Security Council, and 4) Judicial Organization. The material consists of U.N. conference documents, as well as the notes and memorandum to/from Atwood Collins.
  Arrangement
  The material is arranged in four sub-series in order by commission number.
  - Commission I - General Provisions, 1945 May 4 - Jun 23, undated (Box 1, Folder 19-26, Box 2, Folder 1-13)
    This subseries consists of U.N. conference documents pertaining to Commission I - General Provisions. The documents pertain to general commission business and two of its committees; Committee I - Preamble, Purpose, and Principles and Committee II - Membership, Amendment, and Secretariat. The materials include meeting minutes, summaries, reports, as well as memorandum to and from Atwood Collins.
    - Commission I Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Commission I Memorandums, 1945 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Committee I Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 23, undated (Box 1, Folder 21-26, Box 2, Folder 1-4)
    - Committee I Memorandums, 1945 May 14 - Jun 13 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Sub Committee I/A Memorandums, 1945 May 24 - 30 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Committee II Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 7-12)
    - Committee II Memorandums, 1945 May 15 - Jun 18 (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Commission II - General Assembly, 1945 May 4 - Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 15-24, Box 3, Folder 1-22)
    This sub-series consists of documents pertaining to Commission II - General Assembly, as well as its four committees: 1) Committee I - Structure and Procedures, 2) Committee II - Political and Security Functions, 3) Committee III - Economic and Social Corporations, 4) Committee IV - Trusteeship System. The sub-series consists of U.N. Conference documents, as well as notes and memorandum to/from Atwood Collins.
    - Commission II Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 23 (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - Committee I Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 19 (Box 2, Folder 17-20)
    - Committee I Memorandums, 1945 May 11 - circa Jun 18 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Committee I Notes, 1945 May 17 - Jun 6 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
    - Committee II Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 21 (Box 2, Folder 24, Box 3, Folder 1-6)
    - Committee II Memorandums, 1945 May 15 - Jun 18, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Committee II Notes, 1945 May 28; 1945 Jun 21 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Committee III Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 9 (Box 3, Folder 9-13)
    - Committee III Memorandums, 1945 May 15 - Jun 8 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Committee IV Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 21 (Box 3, Folder 15-20)
    - Committee IV Memorandums, 1945 May 14 - Jun 20 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Committee IV Notes, 1945 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Commission III - Security Council, 1945 May 4 - Jun 25, undated (Box 3, Folder 23-28, Box 4, Folder 1-24)
    Scope and Contents
    This series consists of documents pertaining to Commission III - Security Council and its four committees: 1) Committee I - Structure and Procedures; 2) Committee II - Peaceful Settlement; 3) Committee III - Enforecement Arrangements; 4) Regional Arrangements. The material consists of summaries, minutes, and reports from the conference, as well as notes and memorandum to/from Atwood Collins.
    - Commission III Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 25 (Box 3, Folder 23-24)
    - Committee I Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 22 (Box 3, Folder 25-28, Box 4, Folder 1-5)
    - Committee I Memorandums, 1945 May 17 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Committee I Notes, 1945 Jun 19 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Committee II Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 20 (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
    - Committee II Memorandums, 1945 May 17- 24 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Committee III Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 23 (Box 4, Folder 12-17)
    - Committee III Memorandums, 1945 May 21 - 31 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Committee IV Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 15 (Box 4, Folder 19-22)
    - Committee IV Memorandums, 1945 May 21 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Committee IV Notes, 1945 May 20 - Jun 13 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Commission IV - Judicial Organization, 1945 May 4 - Jun 23, undated (Box 4, Folder 25-27, Box 5, Folder 1-19)
    This sub-series contains documents pertaining to Commission IV - Judicial Organization, and its two committees: Committee I - International Court of Justice and Committee II - Legal Problems.
    - Commission Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 23 (Box 4, Folder 25-26)
    - Committee I Documents, 1945 May 4 - Jun 17, undated (Box 4, Folder 27, Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Committee I Memorandums, 1945 May 11 - Jun 14 (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
    - Committee I Notes, 1945 May 10 - Jun 14, undated (Box 5, Folder 11-14)
    - Committee II Documents, 1945 May 5 - Jun 12 (Box 5, Folder 15-18)
    - Committee II Memorandums, 1945 May 17 - Jun 7 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- General U.N. Documents, 1945 Apr 25 - Jun 25 (Box 5, Folder 20-21, Box 6, Folder 1-6)
  The series consists of documents marked "general" which consist of conference information. Many of the documents are lists of published U.N. Documents.
- Plenary Sessions, 1945 Apr 26 - Jun 26; 1945 Apr 26 - May 9 (Box 6, Folder 7-10)
  This series contains the agendas and meeting minutes of the plenary sessions.
- Conference News and Notifications, 1945 Apr 25 - Jun 9, undated (Box 6, Folder 11-20)
  This series consists of different documents released to inform the attendees of the conference. These documents include summaries, agendas, and reading lists.
  This series is broken down further into four parts by the different serial publications that informed attendees: Order of the Day, Précis of Committee Proceedings, U.N. Conference Journal, and digests & suggested readings. Documents are arranged chronologically within each sub-series.
  - Order of the Day, 1945 Apr 25 - Jun 24 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - Precis of Committee Proceedings, 1945 May 5 - Jun 21 (Box 6, Folder 13-16)
  - U.N. Conference Journal, 1945 Apr 25 - Jun 22 (Box 6, Folder 17-19)
  - Digests and Suggested Readings, 1945 May 15; 1945 Jun 9, undated (Box 6, Folder 20)
- Ephemera, Circa 1945 - 1947, undated (Box 6, Folder 21)
- Publications, 1942-1951, undated (Box 6, Folder 22, Box 7, Folder 1-13, Box 8, Folder 1-4, Box 9, Box 10)
  This series consists of publications including directories, booklets, pamphlets, journals, newsletters, New York Times newspapers, and clippings saved by Atwood Collins regarding the San Francisco Conference as well as the United Nations in general. While the majority of the series is not written by Atwood Collins, this series includes a draft of a press release written by Atwood Collins. There is also one hardcover copy of the "Comments and Proposed Amendments Concerning the Dumbarton Oaks Proposals."
- Post U.N. Conference, 1947-1948, undated (Box 8, Folder 5-7)
  Contains reports regarding the U.N. circa 1947-1948.